A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests, Series D FA313
Rockefeller Archive Center
- New York City and New York State
  - New York City and New York State - Golden Jubilee Celebration, 1948, 1947-1950 (Box 17, Folder 108)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller a member of committee. Small donation by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Information (mostly clippings) from newspapers. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - New York City and New York State - Post War Study Group, 1942-1944 (Box 17, Folder 109)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. invited to be member of committee. Interested but declined to serve. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Mayor Fiorello La Guardia.
  - New York City and New York State - World Fashion Center, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 110)
    Plans for expositions in City. Discussion of the Metropolitan Opera's role in creation of Rockefeller Center. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made small contribution to study group. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Mayor LaGuardia, Grover Whalen.
  - New York City and New York State - New York City Planning Commission, 1940-1961 (Box 17, Folder 111)
    No active family interest shown in this file. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard, W. T. Lindquist.
    66.3
  - New York City and New York State - New York City Planning Commission, 1940-1961 (Box 17, Folder 0111A)
    David Rockefeller was a member of advisory panel. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - New York City and New York State - New York City Committee for Latin America Scholarships, Inc., 1942-1952 (Box 17, Folder 112)
    David Rockefeller was a member of committee. No record here of more than one year of activity. Committee liquidated in 1952. International House got residual funds. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
    66.4
  - New York City and New York State - Triborough Bridge Authority, 1950-1959 (Box 17, Folder 113)
    Invitations to bridge and road openings. No family interest expressed. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Robert Moses.
    66.5
  - New York City and New York State - New York State Thruway Authority, 1950-1955 (Box 17, Folder 114)
    Building thruway near Tarrytown. Mrs. Robert C. Hill's concern. Dedication of bridge across Tappan Zee, contribution. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Mrs. Robert C. Hill.
    66.6
  - New York City and New York State - New York State Thruway Authority - Committee to Save the Villages, 1954-1955 (Box 17, Folder 115)
  - New York City and New York State - New York State Citizens Council, 1948-1956 (Box 17, Folder 116)
    Request for contribution. Various reports. Contributions. Little interest shown.
    66.7
  - New York City and New York State - New York State Citizens Council, 1948-1956 (Box 17, Folder 0116A)
  - New York City and New York State - State Committee Against Discrimination, 1946-1957 (Box 17, Folder 117)
    No office interest or participation here. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    66.8
  - New York City and New York State - State Committee Against Discrimination - Housing Advisory Council, 1955-1960 (Box 17, Folder 118)
    W. T. Lindquist served on Council.
- Peoples Institute
  - Peoples Institute, Brooklyn, 1922-1932 (Box 18, Folder 119)
    Community Center work. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. Rockefeller Office refused to underwrite entire program after several years of annual contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard.
    64
  - Peoples Institute, New York, 1901-1932 (Box 18, Folder 120)
    Scientific, ethical, music, practical social science lectures. Information on New York Social Center Committee. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson.
    64.1
- Pocantico Hills Lyceum
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum, 1905-1920 (Box 18, Folder 121)
    Relations between Lyceum and churches. Providing recreation for the young men. Much community interest. Annual gifts by John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Small amounts given through J. H. Nelson. Building converted into fire house, 1934. Fourth of July fireworks. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. leases land. Correspondents include J. H. Nelson, S. H. Bent, J. Hughes, F. J. Heaney, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    64.2
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum, 1921-1935 (Box 18, Folder 122)
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum, 1937-1958 (Box 18, Folder 123)
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum - Insurance, 1940-1958 (Box 18, Folder 124)
    Letters from 1934-1937 were destroyed in 1942.
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum - Lease, 1938-1960 (Box 19, Folder 125)
    Fire House lease and adjoining piece by Pocantico Hills Fire Department.
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum - Pledge - March 21, 1934 for Alteration - Remortgage, 1932-1941 (Box 19, Folder 126)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. finances purchase of building and land from Roberts' heirs. Takes mortgage on property. Property eventually reverts to him. Building used as fire house. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Robert W. Gumbel.
  - Pocantico Hills Lyceum - Roberts Heirs Matter, 1929-1939 (Box 19, Folder 127)
    Property donated to Pocantico in 1894 by Mr. and Mrs. Roberts. Problems of transferring title from heirs, grant under Roberts. Library problems. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Thomas M. Debevoise, W. R. Conklin.
- Hope Chapel, Community House, Tarrytown
  - Hope Chapel Community House, Tarrytown, 1925-1956 (Box 19, Folder 128)
    Presbyterian, but interdenominational in activities. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. makes pledge of $5,000 for Activity house; plans fell through. He gives $25,000 for Community house on smaller site, became Hope Presbyterian Church. Suffered from depression. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Willard S. Richardson.
    64.3
- Police
  - Police - New York Police Department, 1914-1961 (Box 19, Folder 129)
    Aid to slain or retired patrolmen and their families. Invitations to dinners and dedications. Requests for special assistance to department. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Arthur Woods.
    16
  - Police - New York Police Department - Contributions, 1916-1951 (Box 19, Folder 130)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions, tickets purchased.
  - Police - New York Police Department - John Fitzpatrick, 1919-1928 (Box 19, Folder 131)
    Assistance to patrolman at Wall Street & Broadway. Cancer, hospital advice. Death. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, John Fitzpatrick.
  - Police - New York Police Department - John Lang, 1917-1928 (Box 19, Folder 132)
    Aid to patrolman in finding position after retirement. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, John Lang.
  - Police - New York Police Department - Social Service Work, 1914-1917 (Box 19, Folder 133)
    Rockefeller contributions to social work among policemen. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Police - Police Athletic League, 1941-1961 (Box 20, Folder 134)
    Requests for contributions, most declined. Contributors Information Bureau report on Police Athletic League. Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributions. Also from family members. Correspondents include Mayor Fiorello H. LaGuardia, Arthur W. Packard, James B. Nolan, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller, Marilyn Milton Simpson, Alexander Aldrich.
    16.1
  - Police - New York Police Department Honor Legion - Field Day, 1914-1935 (Box 20, Folder 135)
    Rockefeller contributions to special funds for aid to policemen. Annual contributions. Field Day. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods, Robert W. Gumbel.
    16.3
  - Police - Police Societies of Westchester and Tarrytown, 1914-1961 (Box 20, Folder 136)
    Requests for contributions. Contributions. Correspondents include M. S. Beltzhoover, Arthur W. Packard.
    16.4
  - Police - Police Societies of Westchester and Tarrytown - Policemen's Benevolent Association of Westchester County, 1932-1961 (Box 20, Folder 137)
    Contributions from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and sons, including Margaret (Peggy) McGrath Rockefeller. Regular after 1943.
  - Police - Police Societies of Westchester and Tarrytown - Policemen's Benevolent Association of Westchester County, 1932-1961 (Box 20, Folder 0137A)
  - Police - Police Societies of Westchester and Tarrytown - Tarrytown and North Tarrytown Police, 1924-1954 (Box 20, Folder 138)
    Request for John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to contribute to Police Pension Fund. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and John D. Rockefeller, Sr. made contributions.
  - Police - Police Societies of Westchester and Tarrytown - Westchester County Parkway Patrolmens Benevolent Association, 1934-1960 (Box 20, Folder 139)
  - Police - Committee for a State Police, 1914-1917 (Box 20, Folder 140)
    Rockefeller contribution toward program in New York legislature toward enacting a state police force. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller, Sr., O. H. Villard.
    16.5
- Political Organizations
  - Political Organizations - General
    Surge of appeals for aid during each presidential campaign. Consistent Rockefeller referral to policy of giving only to Republican Committees. Declined requests for campaign assistance. Plans and programs for defeating Franklin D. Roosevelt. No real interest shown by Office to 1949. 1928 Campaign requests for financial aid from various candidates. Suggestion that John D. Rockefeller, Jr. run for New York mayor in 1929. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. on Dwight D. Eisenhower. Material from the "lunatic fringe." Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Dana S. Creel.
    128
    - 1920-1937 (Box 21, Folder 141)
    - 1937-1944 (Box 21, Folder 142)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 21, Folder 143)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 21, Folder 144)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 21, Folder 144A)
    - 1955-1961 (Box 22, Folder 145)
  - Political Organizations - Senator Homer C. Capehart, 1949-1952 (Box 22, Folder 146)
    No contributions to his or Senator W. E. Jenner's campaigns.
  - Political Organizations - Citizens' Non-Partisan Committee, 1937-1953 (Box 22, Folder 147)
    Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Nelson A. Rockefeller. Disbanded in 1953.
  - Political Organizations - City Affairs Committee, 1935-1938 (Box 22, Folder 148)
    General committee to do good in city organizations from cleaning Tammany Hall to better schools, housing and taxing policies. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Political Organizations - City Affairs Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 22, Folder 0148A)
  - Political Organizations - Committee of One Hundred, 1909 (Box 22, Folder 149)
    Rockefeller contribution to 1909 campaign by Committee; $2,500 from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in October 1909. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. H. Outerbridge.
  - Political Organizations - Thomas E. Dewey, 1937-1950 (Box 22, Folder 150)
    Contributions toward research. Contributions to campaign declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David French, John F. Dulles, Robert H. Thayer, Thomas M. Debevoise, Frank J. Doyle.
  - Political Organizations - Fusion Committee, 1917-1919 (Box 22, Folder 151)
    Campaigns against Tammany Hall in 1917. Samples of campaign literature. Rockefeller contributions to campaign and resulting deficit. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Political Organizations - Mark Granite, 1936-1958 (Box 22, Folder 152)
    Conservative Republican propagandist. No family interest.
  - Political Organizations - Mayor Fiorello La Guardia, 1937-1945 (Box 22, Folder 153)
    Support by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Nelson A. Rockefeller. Letter to Mayor from "your largest taxpayer, landlord, and friend." Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Mayor Fiorello La Guardia.
    See also the City Fusion Party files, Box 37, Folders 300-301.
  - Political Organizations - United Republican Finance Committee, 1935-1937 (Box 22, Folder 154)
    Purpose was to rebuild the Republican organization and to collect for State, County and National Committees. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. discusses New Deal with Winthrop Aldrich and with John D. Rockefeller, Sr. Rockefeller contributions 1935 and 1937. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., W. Aldrich.
  - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Thomas M. Debevoise Correspondence
    Comments on the New Deal by Thomas M. Debevoise and his acquaintances. Comments by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. on affairs of the nation. Discussion of repeal of 18th Amendment. Thomas M. Debevoise support of Hoover. Comments on Franklin D. Roosevelt and the New Deal. Support for Wendell Willkie. Effect of Hatch Act on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s political contributions. Appeals for political contributions declined. Thomas M. Debevoise handled John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s best wishes to Harry S. Truman. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. followed Citizens Union Voters Directory in voting for local candidates. No contributions to primary campaigns. Generally contributions made only to regular committees. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise, John E. Lockwood.
    - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Thomas M. Debevoise Correspondence, 1928-1938 (Box 23, Folder 155)
    - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Thomas M. Debevoise Correspondence, 1938-1954 (Box 23, Folder 156)
    - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Thomas M. Debevoise Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 23, Folder 157)
    - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Thomas M. Debevoise Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 23, Folder 158)
  - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Letter to James A. Farley, November 7, 1936, 1936-1937 (Box 23, Folder 159)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. congratulates Mr. Farley on his victory speech. Comments on his sportsmanship. Letters published. Some reaction received in mail. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., J. A. Farley.
  - Political Situations - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Statement, September 1936 (Box 23, Folder 160)
    Response to critics of Rockefeller contributions to Republican campaign in Maine. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - David Rockefeller, 1942-1953 (Box 24, Folder 161)
    Appeals for contributions or participation in individual campaigns. Most declined. A few small contributions made for special reasons. Comments on right wing groups. David Rockefeller a member of New York Young Republican Club. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, F. A. Jamieson, Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise, John E. Lockwood.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - David Rockefeller, 1945-1961 (Box 24, Folder 162)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - David Rockefeller, 1957-1960 (Box 24, Folder 163)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - David Rockefeller, 1952-1956 (Box 24, Folder 164)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - David Rockefeller, 1952-1955 (Box 24, Folder 165)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's contributions to save Republican committee. He declined making contributions to the campaigns of individuals. Also declined to serve on committees for candidates. File, however indicates that he did work for his choices. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Thomas M. Debevoise, T. E. Dewey, F. A. Jamieson, H. N. Knowles, John E. Lockwood.
    - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1933-1946 (Box 25, Folder 166)
    - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1947-1954 (Box 25, Folder 167)
    - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1954-1956 (Box 25, Folder 168)
    - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1956-1959 (Box 25, Folder 169)
    - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1960-1961 (Box 26, Folder 170)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, 1955-1958 (Box 26, Folder 171)
    Request for aid, support - no replies. Correspondents include John E. Lockwood.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Laurance S. Rockefeller
    Laurance S. Rockefeller interested in J. N. Garner movement in 1938-1939, but his contributions went to Republican Committee. Made no contributions while in service. H. Stassen and T. Dewey thank Laurance S. Rockefeller for help given. Discussion of members for Dewey's cabinet of 1948. Reports to Laurance S. Rockefeller on Republican chances, 1948 and 1950. Appeals for contributions to campaigns usually declined. Laurance S. Rockefeller served on United Republican Finance Committee.
    - 1936-1950 (Box 26, Folder 172)
    - 1949-1952 (Box 26, Folder 173)
    - 1952-1957 (Box 26, Folder 174)
    - 1952-1957 (Box 26, Folder 174A)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 26, Folder 175)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 26, Folder 176)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Laurance S. Rockefeller - 1950 Appeal Letters (Box 27, Folder 177)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller solicited funds for Republican Finance Committee.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Laurance S. Rockefeller - Contributions, 1936-1946 (Box 27, Folder 178)
    Letters transmitting donations to political campaign.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Laurance S. Rockefeller - 1948 Solicitations (Box 27, Folder 179)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller solicited funds for United Republican Finance Committee.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1936-1957 (Box 27, Folder 180)
    Some of Nelson A. Rockefeller's contributions. Nelson A. Rockefeller's decisions regarding political contributions from him while holding office. Requests from individuals for contributions declined. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Nelson A. Rockefeller Campaign, 1958, 1958-1960 (Box 27, Folder 181)
    Campaign. Congratulations. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, George L. Hinman.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Nelson A. Rockefeller Campaign, 1958, 1958-1960 (Box 27, Folder 0181A)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Nelson A. Rockefeller Campaign, 1958 - Publicity, 1957-1960 (Box 27, Folder 182)
    Clippings on Nelson A. Rockefeller, family, and public opinion.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Winthrop Rockefeller, 1946-1960 (Box 27, Folder 183)
    $3,000 to Friends of Rockefeller and Wilson. Two party system in Arkansas. Correspondents include Winthrop Rockefeller, John E. Lockwood.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1928-1937 (Box 27, Folder 184)
    Support for Hoover, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller supported on Arthur Woods recommendation which was based on Smith's. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions, 1930, 1932, 1934, 1936. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributions to Ohio and New Jersey Republicans. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's contributions. 1937 Family contribution to Thomas Dewey. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise, Arthur Woods.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions - Lists, 1909-1943 (Box 27, Folder 185)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions - Lists, 1938-1959 (Box 27, Folder 186)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1937-1941 (Box 28, Folder 187)
    Contributions increase in Congressional contests because of Supreme Court in 1938. Regular contributions, 1939-1940. In 1941, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed to Virginia Democratic-primary. Includes contribution list. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1941-1945 (Box 28, Folder 188)
    Family contributions to local organizations. Re-election of La Guardia in 1941. Handling of contributions while John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s sons were in the armed forces. 1948, 1949 arranged individually. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1941-1945 (Box 28, Folder 0188A)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1941-1945 (Box 28, Folder 189)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1941-1945 (Box 28, Folder 0189A)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1946-1947 (Box 28, Folder 190)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's contributions to National and State (New York and New Jersey) campaigns, 1943. Family's 1944 contributions. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s 1945 contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1946-1947 (Box 28, Folder 0190A)
  - Political Organizations - Republican Organizations - Contributions, 1946-1947 (Box 28, Folder 191)
  - Political Organizations - Political Contributions
    Policy: 1.Through party committees; 2. Not to individual campaign expenses; 3. Not to local committees in states where no property is owned. Some special contributions on basis of personal interest or friendship. Major gifts to Republican New York County Committee, Republican New York State, United Republican Finance Committee, Republican County Committee of Westchester, National Republican Congressional Committee, National Republican Senatorial Committee, Maine Republican Finance Committee.
    - Political Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1948 (Box 28, Folder 192)
    - Political Contributions - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, 1948 (Box 28, Folder 193)
    - Political Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1948 (Box 28, Folder 194)
    - Political Contributions - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1948 (Box 28, Folder 195)
    - Political Contributions - David Rockefeller, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 196)
    - Political Contributions - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 197)
    - Political Contributions - Abby Rockefeller Pardee, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 198)
    - Political Contributions - Winthrop Rockefeller, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 199)
    - Political Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1949 (Box 29, Folder 200)
    - Political Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1949 (Box 29, Folder 201)
    - Political Contributions - David Rockefeller, 1949 (Box 29, Folder 202)
    - Political Contributions - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1949 (Box 29, Folder 203)
    - Political Contributions - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1949 (Box 29, Folder 204)
    - Political Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1950-1951 (Box 29, Folder 205)
    - Political Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1950-1951 (Box 29, Folder 206)